Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim,
and we're going to do a review
of all the points that we've covered
in this Lam Rim course together.
I think it's 37, Tim or 38?
37, I guess.
Anyway, it's something like that.
[Tim] It's 38. [GMR] 38.
And we're going to go
through... I picked out,
there's about 80 cool ideas
that we have pictures for,
and I picked out about 16.
And this is the purpose of
choosing these photographs,
is to make it easy for all of us
to review the big ideas
that we went through.
It's kind of like a meditation.
So if you're going to do a meditation
on this whole course,
you can go through the pictures one by one
and you can test yourself,
and it's kind of fun.
I finish writing the course
then I go through the
photographs and honestly,
I cannot remember what each one is.
Maybe 90% and then I...
a couple of them I don't
remember why I chose the picture.
And then I remind myself,
and then I won't forget it.
So I think it's a wonderful way to
meditate on the main points
of this whole course.
Let's do a self examination.
Let's look at the 16
most important pictures.
And my friends in this very room
are going to tell me
what's the picture about.
So it's a great teaching technique
is to embarrass your friends.
And then they'd never forget
that they embarrassed themselves
in front of so many people.
This is why we debate in the monastery.
The debates I lost I remember deeply.
The debates I won, I can't remember.
So, all right, here we go.
First picture.
Do you guys remember?
I'll give you a clue.
This had to do with the virus.
Does anybody?
[Student] Sending the virus
to the middle of the sun.
[GMR] Yeah good, sending the
virus to the middle of the sun.
And I don't remember the
temperature difference
but it's amazing. It's incredible.
The temperature is incredible
in the middle of the sun.
And the idea is that bodhicitta,
or the vision of the
bodhisattva jumping from
planet to planet, billions
of planets in a few seconds
and meeting each person
there and taking care
of each person there.
The decision to take care
of each person there,
that's so powerful
that something like COVID is
not going to stand up to it.
If any group in the world
does some serious study
about bodhicitta, we can
easily kill the virus.
It's like sending it to
the middle of the sun.
So that's the first picture
I want you guys to remember,
is the power of this decision
to take care of all the
people in the universe.
All right, second picture, Mr. Pachi.
You guys remember this LAG MTHIL DU GDAMS?
What's it mean?
(unclear)
Yes. The name of this book
is A Gift of Liberation Thrust
Into The Palm of Your Hand.
But there's a different palm
of your hand in scripture
which means to keep something as your
primary practice, this
is my main practice.
Somebody says, "What are
you working on nowadays?"
- Oh, I'm working on
my number one practice.
- What's that?
- I'm trying to get this
vision of a bodhisattva.
So bodhicitta,
which I like to call
vision of a bodhisattva,
that's the main thing I'm focusing on.
That's my main practice I'm focusing on.
So he says, "Put that in
the palm of your hand,"
means keep it,
the world, all the people in
the world and the universe.
That should be your main practice,
and then you're on the right track.
All right, third picture, Mr. Pachi.
Yes I love this picture.
You should get your own.
Find a picture of you with your mom
and keep it for this course.
Find a nice picture of you with your mom.
And it's very important,
during this entire course,
that you keep coming back to
this one person in your
life who took care of you.
It's very important to
keep coming back to her.
And I'll tell you the first
time I saw the picture recently,
I don't look at it all the time,
I was thinking, oh yeah, that's my mom.
But then if you keep looking
at the picture every day,
then I think you cannot help
but go back and realize how much
hardship and love she put
into taking care of you.
And my mom had a lot of hardships,
four sons, no husband
and very, very difficult.
So I think
that's probably the most important picture
for this seven step practice
for reaching a bodhisattva state of mind,
is to keep a picture of your mom
close by and think about it
during this course a lot.
And you'll never forget
that the goal of this course
is to realize that every
single person around you
has done the same thing for you.
All right, next one.
Wait a minute, that's the wrong picture,
you guys sure that's the next one?
I'm thinking Dharmakirti.
Oh no, you're right, you're
right, that's the right one.
Okay, I'm sorry.
Yeah, this was the proof of Dharmakirti.
I was expecting that
picture of Dharmakirti
but this'll do.
And we took a detour
because Pabongka Rinpoche
quoted Dharmakirti,
and I think he wanted us to take a detour
because he cut the
quotation in the middle.
And when it's cut in half,
the quotation means the opposite
of what it's supposed to mean.
So, there's a 'not' at
the end that he left out.
And so, it's not the case
that the DBANG PO,
the clarity of the senses of the child,
the life of the child
and the G-YER BAG CAN,
the personality.
Pau gave me this word,
the unique personality
of Maitri, of this baby,
he has his own personality.
And there can be twins
born at the same time.
Psychologists have trouble with that
because they want to say
their mom ate a milkshake.
Their mom ate a really hot chile relleno
in the third month, and that's
why the kid is so angry.
But they have trouble with twins.
Then they have to say, the
chile relleno went to one twin
but the chile relleno
didn't go to the other twin.
And it gets crazy.
Yes, kids enter this life
with a certain personality,
and their sense powers display life.
They have life.
The personality is not
coming from their skin.
Their personality is not
coming from chemicals.
Because if it was coming from chemicals,
then every time you put
those chemicals in a bottle
you should have Maitri, but you don't.
What children are
is not just the result of chemicals.
Of course, it affects children,
but who they are
is flowing from a similar
cause in the past.
Mind
can only be the result of mind.
Which came first,
the chicken or the egg?
Yes.
Yes, every egg needs a chicken
and every chicken needs an egg.
Yes, therefore, if you can just struggle
to prove that you were alive 10 minutes
before your mom and dad had sex
and the egg was fertilized by the sperm.
If you can just force
your mind 10 minutes back
from that moment,
you have to say you were alive,
something was alive,
something was aware,
you have to say.
If you can push back that 10 minutes,
then everyone's been your mother.
Then it's totally logical.
Then you're already trapped.
Checkmate.
Did you live 10 minutes before?
Yeah. Okay, then everyone's been your mom.
Proof.
It doesn't take a genius.
All right, next one, you guys.
Do you remember this one?
It was an emphasis on
location. Do you remember?
(students talking)
[GMR] Yes. If you've had countless births,
then you have stepped on
or you have been born in every
square meter of the universe.
Countless times, billions of times.
So it's kind of fun, I like
to walk out in the desert,
find a rock.
It's so difficult at Diamond
Mountain to find a rock.
You just walk out and you find one rock
and you say,
"I have been born next to this rock
billions and billions of times".
But it's not a single rock
out in the desert somewhere.
I have been born
at this rock, near this rock
billions of times.
And then you get a feeling
for how many times it's been.
It's very difficult.
It's easy to throw around
the word countless.
We get lazy in Buddhism.
How many lives you live? Countless lives.
Yes, but what does that really mean?
That means you've been born everywhere
billions of times.
Every country, every language,
every world, every planet,
every star,
billions of times.
Try to think like that.
I like to go to Diamond Mountain,
go out
in a black moon, Yamantaka day,
and look at the sky,
you see the Milky Way.
This morning I was
listening to Stevie Wonder,
"Ribbon in the Sky" and I was like,
"Veronica, what's the Ribbon in the Sky?
Maybe it's the Milky Way."
And billions and billions of stars.
I remember a Chinese lady from Shanghai.
I went to Shanghai. I taught in Shanghai.
They told me to stay inside.
Stay in the hotel, don't go outside.
I'm like, "Why?"
And they said, "Look out
the hotel right now".
And I looked to the hotel,
there's another part of the
hotel about 50 feet away.
You couldn't see it.
The pollution was so bad.
And they said, "Don't go outside."
I'm like, "Wow, that's weird."
You can go outside.
And then a lady from China told me,
"Hey, guess what?
I came to Diamond Mountain.
I saw the Milky Way. I saw all the stars.
Can I ask you a question?"
- Yes. What?
- Will these stars be out tomorrow
or is it just tonight?
Do they also have these stars tomorrow?
I'm like, "We have them every night."
She's like, "Wow!
I thought it was just
once a year or something."
Then look at those billions of stars
and think about,
you've been on each one billions of times.
I also like to play a game with myself.
I go out, there's an app, what is that?
Sky App or something?
[Students] Sky Guide
or something like that.
[GMR] What is it called?
Sky Guide.
Get it on your phone, it's so amazing.
And it tells you
what's the name of the star.
I like to play with my Sky Guide
and check out the next
star I'd like to be on
next life.
I say where am I going next?
It's very cool.
All right.
No place we haven't been born.
Next picture, you guys.
Do you remember what this story is?
Come on.
I'll give you a clue, a wolf was involved.
[Student] The story of
the lady who suffers
[GMR] Blue Lotus, Utpala.
Utpala Varman,
Blue Colored Lotus.
And this terrible, terrible story
about this incredible nun
who became an arhat
after she was personally greeted
by the Buddha who stood up
when she entered the garden
and invited her to become a nun.
After she had all her children die,
her parents die, her husbands die,
and after she was buried
alive twice or three times.
What's the point of this story?
Why did they have this story in the book?
[Student] To understand your past life.
[GMR] Yes, there will come a day
when you will see your past life.
There will come a day
when you can see that everyone's
been your mom directly.
So right now, you have
to do it with logic.
But there will come a day
when you just look around
and you think, "Oh my god,
they all have been my mom.
I can remember what they did.
I remember my 10th birthday with her.
And I remember my sixth birthday with her.
And I remember he kicked
me when I was a kid."
And you can see all your past moms.
So the story was very important.
There was an argument that...
don't think that just because
you cannot recognize right now
that someone has been your mother before
that they have never
been your mother because
the passage of life and death
covers,
it obscures
the reality that everyone has
been our mom countless times.
You've died so many
times, you've forgotten.
Next picture.
This one's tough!
If you want to win the $50,
you have to relate it to
another piece of clothing.
[Student] It's related
to the monk's shawl.
[GMR] Yes, great.
It was related to the monk's shawl
and Pabongka was making an argument.
[Student] Dirty shawl, wasn't it?
[GMR] Just because my
shawl has holes in it,
doesn't prove...
[Student] That it wasn't
whole to begin with.
[GMR] Yes, that it's not
the same shawl I bought
in the market last year.
Yes, it looks different,
it's a little worse for wear.
In English, we have this idiom,
worse for wear.
It means look, yeah, my shawl looks like
it's been beaten up 100 times.
That's kind of a funny analogy.
Yes, you're going to run into
people that look like them
and beaten up by live 100 times, but still
they were your fresh, beautiful mom.
They're not different from
the fresh, beautiful mom
in Geshe-la's picture
when he was a little kid.
Just because my monk shawl has holes in it
doesn't prove it's not the same shawl
I bought at the market last year.
Just because the mother
sentient beings around you
look a little worn out,
doesn't mean they weren't that fresh mom
who gave you birth last life.
It's the same mom,
it's just got holes in it.
But just because it has holes doesn't mean
it's not the same mom.
Next picture.
What is this picture?
What's the event?
[Student] It's a Japanese
dancing in the Lam Rim.
[GMR] Yes, it's the Lam
Rim event in Bali, 2019.
Why are we showing it here?
I'll give you the first part of the logic,
it's a logical statement.
If your mom had not been so
skillful at saving your ass
1,000 times every day,
you wouldn't be sitting here
and listening to Lam Rim.
What's the best thing
your mom ever did for you?
Feed you baby food,
give you milk,
save you from falling off the table.
No, she got you here.
So, maybe she's nice.
Maybe she's a nice person.
She got you into the Lam Rim
and that's the best thing
she ever did for you.
I like this picture of the Lam
Rim because it's so joyful.
And she got you there.
Those of you who were there,
it was a very beautiful moment
to see all of our friends
doing their traditional dances
from many countries.
And your mom got you here.
That's the best thing she ever did.
Next one.
Now, next one, somebody has
to tell me the whole story.
I don't want to tell the story.
Who's going to do it? Pachi?
Loud so they can hear it.
[Pachi] This is a story
of Mongolian children
with no parents, wild children.
Don't give for granted.
And they live in the sewer.
If your mom had not worked so hard,
you would be a wild animal.
You would just be a wild animal.
It's not that you're naturally
civilized, you're not.
Your mom civilizes you.
So, take away the mom, like
the kids we saw in Mongolia,
who are living in the sewer.
They cannot speak human language.
They don't understand human language.
They run around naked
and they bite tourists
who don't give them their purse.
You would be the same.
Without your mom,
you would be a wild animal.
And you would be the same.
So think about it.
The difference between you
and a wild animal is your mom.
And I think especially
giving us the gift of speech,
teaching us to speak.
We don't always use it
for the best purpose but
that's an extraordinary gift.
All right, next one.
Somebody tell me the whole story.
For $0.
[Student] If your mom is hitting you
it's like on drug.
[GMR] Yes, your mom
accidentally took some extra...
[Student] Drugs. [GMR] Drugs.
[Student] And she just
got a little bit violent,
she doesn't recognize
you when you're coming
to the room.
You won't shoot her.
You will try to just make her...
[GMR] Peaceful.
So this is the answer
to the question that
people give to Buddhists.
- Are you ahinsa? Do you have ahinsa?
- Are you non-violent? - Yes.
So if somebody comes at you with a knife
and you have a gun, you won't shoot them?
And you're like, "No."
And they say, "Why?"
Well would you shoot your own mother
if she came out at you with a knife?
My mother's not going to come
at me with a knife, come on.
Yes, but if your mother
went temporarily crazy
because she took some drugs by accident,
and she was crazy and she
thought you're a thief,
and she came out at you
with her kitchen knife,
and she's about to kill you,
would you shoot her then?
And you're like, "Hmm."
"You know, I wouldn't shoot
her, I would just grab her
and try to knock her down
and take the knife out of her hand."
Well, would you do that if you knew
she was going to cut you badly?
And then if you're a
good kid, you say, "Yes,
I would allow her to cut me badly
rather than shoot her."
So that's the idea, is that
people around us have temporary insanity.
They do stupid, mean things to us,
but it doesn't mean that
that gives you the right
to hurt them
because they are your mom
and you wouldn't do it to your mom.
If you're a good kid,
you would not shoot a gun at your mom,
even if she's trying to kill you.
You would find a way to try to stop her.
And this applies to countries
that attack your country
and things like that.
Other countries which are
threatening your country.
Is there a way
that you could slow them down or stop them
without hurting them?
And then
when we negotiate with other countries
and we have international problems,
we have to remember
they have been our mom.
All right, next one.
Who wants to tell me what this is?
- Six perfections. -Nice! It's
the six, wait, who wrote this?
I'll give you a clue,
his picture is there.
[Student] This is Arya Nagarjuna.
[GMR] Nagarjuna wrote this
and he went through the six
perfections and he said,
"Here's the
correlations."
Here's the six correlations.
You want to make money?
Can we keep it up?
Sorry, Pachi.
If you are generous to
people, you will become rich.
If you don't hurt other people,
you'll always be happy.
If you want to be beautiful,
don't get upset at people.
If you
are careful to be joyful
when you do your dharma,
then actually people will
recognize you as a leader.
People will accept you as a leader.
And if you meditate regularly,
even lousy meditation,
you will be peaceful.
Because it's karma. It's not
the success of the meditation,
it's the fact that you tried to meditate.
And if you try to remember
that things are coming
from your seeds,
then eventually you'll
be freed from suffering.
Now, I think Christina,
why did I stick this in
this part of the Lam Rim?
Pabongka did not put this
in this part of the Lam Rim.
But he should have.
[Christina] Was it because Chandrakirti
asked the question later
as to how you get to
bodhichitta?
[GMR] Maybe.
[Tim] You can do that or
you can just have love
and then accomplish them all.
[GMR] Yes.
There's the last line there,
Kirpa sarvartha sadhani.
You can do those six perfections or
just love people.
And he kept saying that random
feelings of love from people
for a few minutes
during the day was worth
all the six perfections,
sarvartha sadhani
You can reach all your goals.
What's the correlation for love?
Everything.
Be generous, you get money.
Yes, I got that.
Don't hurt people, you'll be happy.
Be patient, you'll be handsome.
Yes, I got that.
I mean, I wish I could do it.
But love people even for a few minutes,
then you can have everything.
Then the correlation is everything.
Which is the argument for bodhichitta
and especially for compassion.
All right, next picture.
I feel uncomfortable, personally,
with the word bodhichitta
being been used a lot, especially
when people misspell it
with a 'c',
which is not the pronunciation.
It's the technical transliteration.
You don't spell bodhichitta with a C.
It's 'cha', it's C-H, duh.
Please. Don't say bodhi-kita.
Anyway, that word makes me uncomfortable
because it feels so foreign.
You got bodhichitta? I hope
not, I took the vaccinations.
(laughing)
No, no, it's a good thing.
Yeah, well what is it?
So what is it?
You got to imagine
sitting in a meditation
in your living room
and walking between a billion
planets within 20 minutes.
You got to imagine
sitting on your meditation
cushion in your living room
and walking on a billion
planets in reality.
Really stepping from planet to planet,
billions of planets,
and personally meeting
each being on each planet.
Each bug, each bird, each fish
and promising them that
you will take care of them.
You got to imagine
having that experience.
And if you have that experience,
then the rest of your life is easy.
Then the rest of your life
is ridiculously easy.
If you just have that
10, 20 minute experience,
then it doesn't matter what happens
for the rest of your life,
you are extraordinarily happy.
And that's bodhichitta.
Please don't think it's
some Buddhist weird thing.
It's not that.
- Is it weird? - Yes.
- Is it unusual? - Yes.
- Is it an experience you
didn't hear about in university?
- Yes.
And it's the most beautiful
experience that a human being
can undertake.
And you will never forget it.
Then your whole life will have
a clear purpose.
You know what you have
to do in this world.
And it's very, very
relaxing and comforting.
You know what your job is.
Nowadays, we're restructuring
one of our companies
and people are like, "What's
my job? What's my job?"
I said, "Don't worry, I'm
going to write your job down."
And once you write the job
down on a piece of paper
and you hand it to them and
say, "This is your job."
And they say, "dot, dot, dot, dot, dot"
and they're like, "Ah!"
At the end of the interview, I say,
"Here's your business card."
And they're like, "Oh man,
I have a title. This is who I am.
Vice President, Operations.
Now I have a title".
And the point is
you get this bodhisattva business card
that says, "Tim Lowenhaupt, Bodhisattva".
Then you're like, "Ah, yeah!
Now I know who I am.
Now I know which company I work for.
And I know what's my position.
I have a position."
And it feels great.
That's your lifetime position.
All right, next one.
So please don't think about bodhichitta
as some minor Buddhist
thing with a Sanskrit name.
It's a lifetime experience.
Once in a lifetime experience.
All right. Here we go.
Who's going to explain this one to me?
It was a long time ago.
[Tim] There's no difference between
the sheep that's going to be killed today
and the sheep that's
hanging out in the pasture
enjoying the grass.
[GMR] Yes, good, good.
[Tim] They all end up the same.
And it's the same here
at the Peach Tree Cafe.
The people are enjoying
themselves, they're having a meal.
But at the end of the day,
we're all heading towards the same place,
we're all in the same plane.
[GMR] Yes. Cool.
Each of these people,
each person here
is laying in a hospital bed
taking their last few breaths after
a failed fight with cancer.
I always think it's so funny they say,
"After a brave battle with cancer."
Come on, battles with
cancer are always one sided.
You die.
So each person here,
who's eating the famous cinnamon roll
at the Peach Tree Cafe,
they're as good as a
person dying in a hospital.
They just look different.
Then don't forget, they have been our mom.
So we have to take care of them.
We should try to help them.
All right, next picture.
Somebody tell me
why this picture is the
same as the last picture.
[Gyelse] Because they're young people,
they're vibrant, and alive, and everything
is going for them, but
they're also going to die.
[GMR] Yes. There're also laying in a bed
in the hospital room
breathing their last breath
except they have a worst disadvantage.
The excitement of life.
They're doing small bad things
to get this new house
and to get this nice job
and to buy that nice
shirt and that nice dress.
They're not cruel people.
They didn't put people in
the gas chamber or something,
they're not like that.
They are normal people.
They are doing small
things to ignore other people
and to hurt other people.
They're not bad people, but
they are constantly collecting
small seeds
that will multiply and bring
them huge suffering later.
These people are suffering as much
as a 90 year old woman
on the resuscitator,
on oxygen in the hospital, dying.
These people are the same.
In fact, these people are worse
because they're collecting karma to be
in that hospital bed 1,000 times,
in this real estate interview,
during this real estate interview.
All right, next.
Got two more to go.
And this is called TSAD,
and Tim's going to explain it, TSAD.
Talk louder, talk louder.
[im] She's at home having
breakfast, but her daughter,
her baby's in the hospital, sick.
And she can't think about anything else
but her sick daughter.
And so she is... TSAD means to measure.
She knows that she has something
but I don't remember what it is right now.
[GMR] How do we know when we got to-
[Tim] How do we know when we have love?
[GMR] Compassion.
How do we know?
Okay, if I ask you,
what did Pabongka Rinpoche say
was the sign
that you have reached the goal
of developing compassion?
[Tim] Personal responsibility.
[GMR] Or even while you're-
[Paulina] You only think about it.
[GMR] Yes, you can't
stop thinking about it.
Mainly it's that. You can't
Any more than a mom could stop
thinking about her daughter
who's in the hospital
after a bad car accident
the night before.
I have a friend who had a lung operation
in the last week or two.
They cut out half of one of his lungs.
He's young. He's very successful.
He's handsome. He's kind.
He has two beautiful kids.
And to talk to his wife
during that day that he was
getting his lung cut out,
she wasn't thinking about anything else.
She wasn't like, "Geshe-la
how's the weather in Sedona?"
She's only focused on one thing.
That's the measure -- TSAD --
that you have compassion.
When you're thinking
like that all the time.
I don't know if you can
enjoy coffee, probably.
If you're super
meditator you can have
coffee and worry about people
at the same time.
Okay, we got one more to go.
And Pachi offered to explain it.
(students laughing)
Loud, okay?
[Pachi] She's taking
personal responsibility.
[GMR] Yes.
By the way, usually when they explain it,
they do it this way.
Look,
I'm going to take responsibility
that plastic doesn't spread in the world.
Me and V were
eating tsampa this morning
and we got it from Tibet.
And it comes in a cloth bag
and V was like, "Wow, we could wash this
and use it again."
I'm like, "Duh."
And then she said, "Probably
people used to do that."
I'm like, "Yeah, I guess so."
You just wash the bag again
and then you put more tsampa in it.
So if you decide, I won't use plastic.
We were talking about our friend Añjali.
She decided to be careful with packaging.
She puts all her garbage in
a box like this every week.
We have 24 bags of stuff
and if we just decide, each person,
I don't know what the rest
of the world is going to do.
I know when they're
driving these big trucks
and using gas they don't have to use.
I know they're throwing
away all kinds of plastic
every moment.
But I personally have made a decision
that I will pick up garbage
than I see on the road.
Or I will be the one who
picks up the garbage quietly
and throws it in the garbage can
for everybody else.
And that's a quiet,
modest,
personal decision that you make
to serve other people,
even if they don't know
and serve future generations.
I will take care.
I'll be the one, I'll start.
I'll take care of future generations.
And I will take care of this world.
I will do my little part
to pass this world on
to the next generation a little cleaner.
Or some kind of personal
responsibility like that.
So that's the sixth step
of developing bodhichitta
and then next course
we're going to go into
what does it feel like
when you hit #7,
which is a famous result of the first six.
So next course, we'll be going into
what does it feel like when you get there?
Okay. I'd like to thank Tim Lowenhaupt
for working so hard.
He works all day, all night.
His work to run these hotels in this town,
pays my salary, thank you for that.
And a lot of other people's livelihood.
And because of him,
I have a refrigerator, et cetera.
Then he also took responsibility
to produce these Lam Rims.
And I think the greatest
achievement he did
was that he attracted,
he is a nice person,
and he has attracted many, many
volunteers around the world
to help
because he's such a nice person.
So thank you for that.
And thank you, Pachi and Pau
for flying up from Mexico
to run all this equipment
because grandpa in 1,000 years
could never run this equipment.
Venerable Gyalse thank
you for Diamond Mountain.
Venerable Connie thank you for YSI
and keeping us healthy
and keeping us going.
And Christina Kasica,
thank you for quietly, anonymously
taking care of all our needs.
It's very graceful and very
elegant and thank you for that.
Okay. And thank you Venerable Jigme
for driving me around
so I can get the Lam Rim done in the car.
See you guys at the next Lam Rim. Yay!